Fabrizio Marinelli

E-mail: fabrizio.marinelli@nih.gov https://sites.google.com/site/fabriziomarinelli/ National Heart, Lung, & Blood Institute
Building 10, Room 5N319
10 Center Dr, Bethesda
MD, 20814, USA
Phone: +1 301 827 0825

PERSONAL STATEMENT

The aim of my research is to characterize the molecular mechanisms of prominent biomolecules involved in membrane transport and/or cell signaling. The premise of my studies is that a deeper molecular understanding of such processes will help identifying more effective therapeutic agents for pathophysiological conditions.

My studies entail the use of computationally intensive molecular simulation techniques and are often performed in synergy with experimental collaborators such as structural biologists and biophysicists.

Part of my research efforts is devoted to the development of efficient and rigorous simulation methods to investigate the structural dynamics of biomolecules and to combine simulations and experimental/bioinformatics data.

POSITIONS

National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Theoretical Molecular Biophysics Section, Bethesda, MD, USA Staff Scientist.	Apr 2016-
National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Theoretical Molecular Biophysics Section, Bethesda, MD, USA Visiting Fellow. Advisor: Dr. José Faraldo-Gómez	Aug 2013-Apr 2016
Max Planck Institute of Biophysics, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, Theoretical Molecular Biophysics Department Postdoctoral Researcher. Advisor: Dr. José Faraldo-Gómez	Nov 2009 – Aug 2013
International School for Advanced Studies (SISSA/ISAS), Statistical and Biological Physics Sector. Trieste, Italy PhD student. Advisor: Prof. Alessandro Laio	Nov 2005 – Oct 2009
EDUCATION	
PhD Statistical and Biological Physics, SISSA/ISAS, Trieste, Italy	Nov 2005 – Oct 2009
MS Chemistry, "La Sapienza" University, Rome, Italy	Oct 1998 – Feb 2005
PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP & ACTIVITIES	
Member of the Biophysical Society	2009-
Member of the American Chemical Society	2013, 2018-
Member of the Society of General Physiologists	2018-

HONORS & AWARDS

Selected for junior investigator presentation at the GRC conference (Machanisms of Mamhana Transport)	Jun 2015
'Mechanisms of Membrane Transport'.Invited reviewer for the national grants of the Czech Science Foundation	Jul 2014
• Selected for junior investigator presentation at the GRC conference 'Protons	Feb 2014
Membrane reactions'.Max Planck Institute of Biophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship, Frankfurt am	Nov 2009 – Aug 2013
Main, Germany.	
SISSA/ISAS PhD Fellowship, Trieste, Italy	Nov 2005 – Oct 2009
Magna cum laude MS Chemistry	Feb 2005
EDITORIAL & ACADEMIC SERVICE	
EDITORIAL BOARD MEMBER (publons.com/a/1375462/)	
• Scientific Reports (Nature Publishing Group)	2018
REVIEWER (publons.com/a/1375462/)	
• eLife	2018
The Journal of General Physiology	2018
Communications Biology (Nature)	2018
 Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics (Wiley) 	2018
BBA Biomembranes (Elsevier)	2017
Scientific Reports (Nature)	2015
 European Biophysics Journal (Springer) 	2015
The Journal of Physical Chemistry (ACS)	2013
 Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation (ACS) 	2012
Biophysical Journal (Cell Press)	2010
SCIENTIFIC SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT	
 Member of the PLUMED consortium [Link] 	2019
 Developer of the Colvars simulation software (C++) [Link] 	2015
• Co-contributor to the PLUMED (version 2) simulation software (C/C++) [Link]	2013
 Co-developer of the METAGUI simulation analysis tool (Tcl/fortran) [Link] 	2011
 Co-developer of the PLUMED (version 1) simulation software (ANSI C) 	2009 –201
INVITED SEMINARS & CONFERENCE TALKS	
POSTDOCTORAL	
• EPR Symposium, Rocky Mountain Conference, Denver, CO, USA	201
 Snowmass Summer Biophysics Workshop, Snowmass, CO, USA 	201
• Gordon Research Conference, 'Mechanisms of Membrane Transport'. Lewisto	
 NIH Tenure-track investigator job interview. National Institute on Drug Institutes of Health, Baltimore, MD, USA 	Abuse, National 201
mattates of ficultifi, builtimore, Mib, Osh	

• CNRS Research Scientist job interview. Physical, Theoretical and Analytical Chemistry. Paris, 2014 France CNRS Research Scientist job interview. Modeling and Analysis of Biological Data and Systems. 2014 Paris, France. CNRS Research Scientist job interview. Chemistry for Living Systems and Medicinal Chemistry. 2014 Paris. France 2014 Gordon Research Conference, 'Protons & Membrane reactions'. Ventura, CA, USA. • Membrane Protein Interest Group and Structural Biology Interest Group Postdoc 2014 Symposium, NIH, Bethesda MD, USA • Biophysical Society Annual Meeting, San Francisco, CA, USA 2014 Assistant professor job interview at Universidad de la República, Paysandú, Uruguay 2013 2012 PLUMED developers and contributors meeting, Trieste, Italy • European Bioenergetics Conference (EBEC), Freiburg, Germany 2012 • Universidad de la República, Montevideo, Uruguay 2012 • Pasteur Institute, Montevideo, Uruguay • CECAM Workshop, 'Exploring Protein Interactions through Theory and Experiment's, 2012 Lausanne, Switzerland • Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Laussane, Switzerland 2011 • Biophysical Society Annual Meeting, Baltimore MD, USA 2011 • German Research School for Simulation Sciences, Jülich, Germany 2010 PhD STUDENT • International Workshop (CECAM), 'From Structure to Function: Influx and Efflux Systems', 2009 Cagliari, Italy. • Mini symposium, Angelos Michaelides group, UCL university, London, England. 2008 • Marie Curie Training Course (CECAM), 'Progress in simulating activated events', Casaprota, 2008 Italy. **TEACHING & MENTORING** LECTURE SERIES & WORKSHOPS Course on Enhanced sampling techniques in classical MD simulations, QUITEL 2016, 2016 Montevideo, Uruguay. • Invited lectures on membrane protein atomistic simulations at the membrane 2013 transporters seminar series, Max Planck Institute of Biophysics, Max Planck Institute of Biophysics, Frankfurt, Germany • Computer Lab of the IMPReS course on modeling & simulation, Max Planck Institute 2010 of Biophysics, Frankfurt, Germany • Computer Lab of Current Techniques in Membrane Proteomics (Module C1) summer 2010 school, Goethe University of Frankfurt, Germany • Invited lectures on kinetics and thermodynamics from biased simulations at the 2009 advanced sampling techniques for numerical simulations Ph.D. course, SISSA, Trieste, Italy (in collaboration with Prof. Alessandro Laio). Invited lectures on quantum chemistry methods at the computational chemistry 2005 course, University "La Sapienza", Rome, Italy (in collaboration with Dr. Luigi Bencivenni).

 Teaching assistant at Physical Chemistry laboratory course, University "La Sapienza", Rome, Italy 	2002-2004
MENTORING	
 Co-supervisor of Dr. Rahul Banerjee and Dr. Wenchang Zhou in the Theoretical molecular biophysics section (NHLBI, NIH) 	Currently
 Co-supervisor of Dr. Richard Bradshaw in the Computational Structural Biology Section (NINDS, NIH) 	Currently
 Co-supervised Irina Shlosman, post baccalaureate in the Theoretical molecular biophysics section (NHLBI, NIH) 	2016-2018
 Co-supervised Corinne Nief, summer student in in the Theoretical molecular biophysics laboratory (NHLBI, NIH) 	2015
• Co-supervised the Ph.D. research of Carles Corbi-Verge (Ph.D. obtained in late 2012)	2011-2013

2002 2004

PUBLICATION LIST

- (•) denotes corresponding authorship
- (#) denotes equal first author contribution.

Research articles and reviews

POSTDOCTORAL

- 1. Fiorin G, Marinelli F and Faraldo-Gómez JD (2019). Direct derivation of free energies of membrane deformation and other solvent density fluctuations from molecular dynamics simulations. *J Comput Chem. Accepted.*
- 2. Bonomi M, Bussi G, Camilloni C, Tribello G, ..., <u>Marinelli F</u>, et al. (2019) Promoting transparency and reproducibility in enhanced molecular simulations. *Nature Methods* 16: 670–673. [<u>Abstract</u>]
- 3. Li M, Wang Y, Banerjee R, Marinelli F, Silberberg S, Faraldo-Gómez JD, Hattori M, Swartz KJ. Molecular mechanisms of human P2X3 receptor channel activation and modulation by divalent cation bound ATP (2019). *eLife* 8:e47060. [Abstract]
- 4. <u>Marinelli F●</u>, G. Fiorin (2018). Structural characterization of biomolecules through atomistic simulations guided by DEER measurements. *Structure* 27:359-370. [Abstract].
- 5. Hustedt E, Marinelli F#, Stein R, Faraldo-Gómez JD, Mchaourab H (2018). Confidence Analysis of DEER Data and its Structural Interpretation with Ensemble-Biased Metadynamics. *Biophys. J.* 115: 1200-16. [Abstract]
- 6. Shlosman I, <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD, Mindell JA (2017). The prokaryotic Na+/Ca2+ exchanger NCX_Mj transports Na+ and Ca2+ in a 3:1 stoichiometry. *J Gen Physiol*. 150:51-65. [Abstract]
- 7. Zhou W, Marinelli F●, Nief C, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2017). Atomistic simulations indicate the c-subunit ring of the F1Fo ATP synthase is not the mitochondrial permeability transition pore. *eLife* 6: e23781. [Abstract]
- 8. Liao J, Marinelli F#, Lee C, Huang Y, Faraldo-Gómez JD, Jiang Y (2016). Mechanism of extracellular ion exchange and binding-site occlusion in the sodium-calcium exchanger. *Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.* 23: 590–599. [Abstract]

- 9. <u>Marinelli F●</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2015). Ensemble-Biased Metadynamics: A Molecular Simulation Method to Sample Experimental Distributions. *Biophys. J.* 108:2779-82. [Abstract]
- 10. Branduardi D, Marinelli F, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2015). Atomic-resolution dissection of the energetics and mechanism of isomerization of hydrated ATP-Mg²⁺ through the SOMA string method. *J. Comput. Chem.*, DOI: 10.1002/jcc.23991. [Abstract]
- 11. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Almagor L, Hiller R, Giladi M, Khananshvili D, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2014). Sodium recognition by the Na⁺/Ca²⁺ exchanger in the outward-facing conformation. *Proc Natl Acad Sci USA* 111:E5354-62. [Abstract]
- 12. Corbi-Verge C, Marinelli F#, Zafra-Ruano A, Ruiz-Sanz J, Luque I, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2013). Two-state dynamics of the SH3-SH2 tandem of Abl kinase and the allosteric role of the N-cap. *Proc Natl Acad Sci USA* 110:E3372-80. [Abstract]
- 13. <u>Marinelli F●</u> (2013). Following easy slope paths on a free energy landscape: the case study of the Trp- Cage folding mechanism. *Biophys J* 105:1236-47. [Abstract]
- 14. <u>Marinelli F●</u>, Sorrenti A, Corvaglia V, Leone V, Mancini G (2012). Molecular description of the propagation of chirality from molecules to complex systems: different mechanisms controlled by hydrophobic interactions. *Chem Eur J* 18:14680–88. [Abstract]
- 15. Biarnés X, Pietrucci F, Marinelli F, Laio A (2012). METAGUI. A VMD interface for analyzing metadynamics and molecular dynamics simulations. *Comput Phys Commun* 183:203-11. [Abstract]
- 16. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Kuhlmann SI, Grell E, Kunte HJ, Ziegler C, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2011). Evidence for an allosteric mechanism of substrate release from membrane-transporter accessory binding proteins. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA, 108:E1285-92. [Abstract]
- 17. Leone V, Marinelli F, Carloni P, Parrinello M (2010). Targeting biomolecular flexibility with metadynamics. *Curr Opin Struct Biol*, 20:148-54. [Abstract]. REVIEW (refereed)

PhD STUDENT

- 18. Crespo Y, Marinelli F●, Pietrucci F, Laio A (2010). Metadynamics convergence law in a multidimensional system. *Phys Rev E* 81:055701. [Abstract]
- 19. Cossio P, Marinelli F, Laio A, Pietrucci F (2010). Optimizing the performance of Bias-Exchange Metadynamics: folding a 48-residue LysM domain using a coarse-grained model. *J Phys Chem B* 114:3259-65. [Abstract]
- 20. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Pietrucci F, Laio A, Piana S (2009). A kinetic model of Trp-cage folding from multiple biased molecular dynamics simulations. *PLoS Comput Biol* 5:e1000452 doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000452. [Abstract]
- 21. Pietrucci F, Marinelli F, Carloni P, Laio A (2009). Substrate binding mechanism of HIV-1 protease from explicit solvent atomistic simulations. *J Am Chem Soc* 131:11811–18. [Abstract]
- 22. Bonomi M, Branduardi D, Bussi G, Camilloni C, Provasi D, Raiteri P, Donadio D, Marinelli F, Pietrucci F, Broglia RA, Parrinello M (2009). PLUMED: A portable plugin for free-energy calculations with molecular dynamics *Comput Phys Commun* 180:1961-72. [Abstract]
- 23. Todorova N, Marinelli F, Piana S, Yarovsky I (2009). Exploring the folding free energy landscape of insulin using bias exchange metadynamics. *J Phys Chem B* 113:3556-64. [Abstract]

24. Piana S, Laio A, Marinelli F, Van Troys M, Bourry D, Ampe C, Martins JC (2008). Predicting the effect of a point mutation on a protein fold: the villin and advillin headpieces and their Pro62Ala mutants. *J Mol Biol* 375:460-70. [Abstract]

MS STUDENT

- 25. D'Abramo M, Aschi M, <u>Marinelli F</u>, Di Nola A, Amadei A (2007). Theoretical prediction of thermodynamic equilibrium constants of chemical reactions in water. *J Mol Structure Theochem* 811:197–201. [Abstract]
- 26. Amadei A, Marinelli F, D'Abramo M, D'Alessandro M, Anselmi M, Di Nola A, Aschi M (2005). Theoretical modeling of vibroelectronic quantum states in complex molecular systems: Solvated carbon monoxide, a test case. *J Chem Phys* 122:124506. [Abstract]
- 27. D'Alessandro M, <u>Marinelli F</u>, D'Abramo M, Aschi M, Di Nola A, Amadei A (2005). Ground and excited electronic state thermodynamics of aqueous carbon monoxide: A theoretical study. *J Chem Phys* 122:124507. [Abstract]

Conference Abstracts

- 1. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Ficici E, Faraldo-Gómez J (2019). Molecular Basis for Ion Recognition and Transport in a Na+/Ca2+ Exchanger. *62th Biophysical Society Annual Meeting*. Baltimore, MD, USA.
- 2. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Ficici E, Faraldo-Gómez J (2018). How the Substrate Occupancy of a Membrane Transporter Determines the Viability of its Alternating-Access Mechanism and thus its Functional Specificity. 61th Biophysical Society Annual Meeting. San Francisco, CA, USA.
- 3. <u>Marinelli F</u>, (2017). Molecular Breakdown of Double Electron-Electron Resonance Data with Atomistic Simulations. *Biophysical Society Thematic Meeting: Conformational Ensembles from Experimental Data and Computer Simulations*. Berlin, Germany.
- 4. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2017). Molecular mechanism of ion exchange and binding-site occlusion in a sodium/calcium exchanger. *Gordon Research Conference, Mechanisms of Membrane Transport*. Colby-Sawyer College, New London, NH, USA.
- 5. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2017). Molecular Breakdown of Double Electron-Electron Resonance Data with Atomistic Simulations. *61*th *Biophysical Society Annual Meeting*. New Orleans, LA, USA.
- 6. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2016). Keeping Secondary Transporters under Control: Lessons from a Na⁺/Ca²⁺ Exchanger. *60*th *Biophysical Society Annual Meeting*. Los Angeles, CA, USA.
- 7. Marinelli F (2015). Ion Occupancy Shapes Conformational Free-Energy Landscape of a Na⁺/Ca²⁺ Exchanger and Allosterically Controls Its Alternating-Access Mechanism. *Gordon Research Conference, Mechanisms of Membrane Transport*. Bates College, Lewiston, ME, USA.
- 8. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2015). Minimally-biased Metadynamics method to sample conformational ensembles compatible with experimental measurements. *59*th *Biophysical Society Annual Meeting*. Baltimore MD, USA.
- 9. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2014). Molecular basis for ion binding and conformational change in the Na⁺/Ca²⁺ exchanger. *Gordon Research Conference, Protons & Membrane Reaction*. Ventura CA, USA.

- 10. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2014). Molecular basis for sodium versus calcium binding in the sodium-calcium exchanger. 58th Biophysical Society Meeting. San Francisco CA, USA.
- 11. Marinelli F, Faraldo-Gómez JD (2013). Molecular basis for Na^+ vs Ca^{2+} binding to the Na^+/Ca^{2+} exchanger. Gordon Research Conference, Mechanisms of Membrane Transport. Mount Holyoke College South Hadley, MA, USA.
- 12. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Faraldo-Gómez, JD (2012). Insights into the mechanism of the Na⁺/Ca²⁺ exchanger from atomistic dynamics simulations 16th. European Bioenergetics Conference. Freiburg, Germany.
- 13. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Kuhlmann SI, Grell E, Bienert R, Kunte H-J, Ziegler C, Faraldo-Gómez J.D (2011). Enhanced substrate release from a TRAP transporter binding protein by allosteric reduction of Its affinity. *Gordon Research Conference, Mechanisms of Membrane Transport*. University of New England, Biddeford, ME, USA.
- 14. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Kuhlmann S.I., Grell E, Bienert R, Kunte H-J, Ziegler C, Faraldo-Gómez J.D. (2011). Enhanced substrate release from a trap transporter binding protein by remote modulation of its intrinsic conformational dynamics. 55th Biophysical Society Annual Meeting. Baltimore MD, USA.
- 15. <u>Marinelli F</u>, Piana S, Pietrucci F, Torodova N, Yarovsky I, Laio A (2009). Insights on protein structure and dynamics from multiple biased molecular dynamics simulations. 53rd Biophysical Society Annual Meeting. Boston MA, USA.

BIBLIOMETRICS (Source: Google scholar, 07/12/2019)
Since 2009: 2005 citations (average of 77 per article), H-index = 17